Well, hello. I'm Derek Rdney. Uh, I'm a
pastor at Trinity Church in Winston
Salem, and I'm hosting this conversation
today on behalf of the Alliance for
Mission and Renewal. The Alliance exists
to help foster a unified, faithful, and
flourishing PCA, and you can go to
a4mr.org
to learn more about who we are and what
we're working for within the PCA. Uh now
part of being a flourishing PCA is being
a denomination where we have enough
qualified pastors preaching in our
churches and planting new churches. So
today I've invited two uh PCA teaching
elders who are seminary presidents to
talk to us about the challenges we're
facing in raising up future pastors. So
with that allow me to introduce my guest
today. Uh first uh I've got Dr. Lianigan
Duncan who is the chancellor and CEO of
Reformed Theological Seminary um which
is located in Charlotte, uh Orlando,
Atlanta, Washington DC, Houston, Dallas,
New York City, and I think other places.
And he's the president uh of the
Jackson, Mississippi campus. Uh, Lian
was ordained in the PCA 1990 and he
served as a professor and a pastor ever
since. Uh, before becoming the
chancellor in 2013, he served as the
senior pastor of First Presbyterian in
Jackson, Mississippi. He received his BA
in history from Ferman uh his Mdive and
Master of Arts from Covenant Theological
Seminary and his PhD from Edinburghough
in uh New College, Scotland. He was
published widely uh or he has been
published widely on a range of topics.
I'm not going to even try to list them
all. Uh and he has served as the
moderator of the PCA in Pittsburgh in
2004. I could say a lot more, but Dr.
Duncan, welcome. Thank you for being
with us.
>> Glad to be here, Derek. Thank you for
having me.
>> Uh my other guest is uh Dr. Tom Gibbs.
He's the sixth president of the PCA's
Covenant Theological Seminary in St.
Louis. uh before taking his role in
2021, he served as a pastor for 24
years. Uh he planted and served as the
pastor of Redeemer Press in San Antonio
for about 19 years and he started and
served at RUF uh at Baylor University
before that. He's also served as the
chair of the Southwest Church Planting
Network and he helped facilitate the
planting of dozens of churches across
four states. He received his
undergraduate degree from Auburn, his
Mdive and Dmen from Covenant Theological
Seminary, and he's been married to
Terara for 32 years, and they have four
children. So, Dr. Gibbs, uh, welcome and
thank you for being here.
>> Derek, it's a privilege to be here and
excited that Lian, you're here with us.
Uh, excited about this discussion.
>> Well, wonderful. Um, so here's what I
want to do to begin. And I'm going to
describe what uh kind of I've heard and
from a lot of different sources is a
problem that um not only our
denomination but many denominations and
really many institutions are facing. And
that's just um well particularly with
churches, it's the approaching pastoral
shortages that we can see coming up in
the next decade or so. So what I've
heard is that in the coming decades,
it's very likely that churches are going
to struggle to fill pastoral vacancies.
Uh right now already many smaller and
rural churches are already facing that
challenge. They're they're having a hard
time finding pastors. And it's not just
a challenge for churches. Uh it's a
demographic challenge that a lot of
institutions are facing. A huge number
uh of men in the PCA are fixing to
retire in the next decade. Um but as
Ryan Burge, who is a political scientist
and a statistician and a professor at
Washington University in St. Lewis has
been kind of putting out there quite a
bit. Uh when the boomers die and there
those are men who are aged 62 to 80 when
they die many denominations are going to
face dramatic declines. Um so for
instance if you look at the adult
population of many of the major
denominations like the UMC about 50% of
their adult members are are boomers. Uh
in the Episcopal Church it's 49%. In the
SBC it's 45 in the Assemblies of God
it's 45. And I think if I've got this
right, in the PCA it's around 40. Uh and
in fact 56% of our adult members are are
over 60 generally. So we're we're in
that mix of of denominations that are in
kind of in danger of having a lot of
boomers passing away. We're going to see
a huge transfer of wealth that's going
to take place, but there's going to be a
potential shortage in ministers. Now, I
don't think it's only demographic from
what I've understood. Um there's a lot
of um changes in what men, young men are
interested in doing with their lives. In
the past, being a pastor was perhaps uh
somewhat prestigious. It was often maybe
a little bit more stable, but as you
guys know, being a pastor is a hard job.
It's risky. Um it doesn't pay well
usually. There's not a lot of social
status linked with being a pastor
anymore. And so it seems like we're
seeing a decline in people even
interested in the ministry. So, um, with
all that said, it seems to me that the
PCA needs to have our eye on this
potential crisis coming up, a huge
shortage of pastors. So, I'd first like
to just hear from you men. Uh, do you
agree with the assessment of the
situation? Uh, if not, how would you see
it? What would you see differently? And
if so, how else would you describe the
challenge? So, I'm going to start with
you, uh, Lian, if you don't mind. And,
yeah, love to hear your thoughts on
this. No, no, Derek, I think you've
accurately described the situation. Uh
we've we've got folks at RTS both
working with folks like Murray Lee, and
I know that I know that Tom is as well,
uh at PCA M&A, uh and with people like
Ryan Burge, Michael Graham, who's an RTS
Orlando graduate, actually co- has
co-authored with uh with Ryan. I love
Ryan's stuff. I read everything that he
does. Um, and we had already started
seeing this at RTS
uh, in a couple of different ways. If
you would asked me 10 or 15 years ago,
Derek, I would have said we had
[clears throat] too many teaching elders
Yeah.
>> in the PCA for available positions. And
I've I in the last 5 years I have
started to see more and more churches
come after guys that haven't finished
their degree in order to go into either
an RUF ministry or into a local church
uh and and sort of do supply until they
could be ordained and then be ordained
uh in the saddle as it as it were. And
that let me know that there were not
enough available people for the
positions that are out there in the PCA.
And so David Velcamp, who is our chief
enrollment management officer, started
working with Murray Lee and then with
leaders from other uh denominations in
Napark and outside of Napark like uh uh
ECO and uh the uh the EPC and some other
reformed and reformed adjacent
denominations and all of them were
seeing the same thing. some more
dramatically than others. Uh across
Napark and just a little bit outside of
it, we reckon that almost every
denomination was somewhere between 10
and 25% short of the pastors that they
needed to fill present pulpits, do new
church plants, and do campus ministry in
new places. M
>> and so we started asking ourselves the
question, what do we need to do about
it? So it's a it's a current reality and
I think the demographics say that it's
probably going to even greater reality 5
to 10 years down the road. We need to
start planning for it now. And I think
Tom is doing this at Covenant. Uh, I I
think I think our all of our traditional
reformed seminaries are aware of this
and we're all trying to figure out
what's the right thing to do, but I
agree with the general assessment. Over
to you, Tom.
>> Yeah.
>> Well, I I agree with what Le is saying
and uh, you know, dipping in the same
wells that he's referring to and same
conversation partners. Uh I I I think
there's a there's a couple of things
that are fascinating about this question
as it relates to the PCA specifically
because we're continuing to see the PCA
uh as an outlier denomination in terms
of church growth and even uh in our
candidates and our lensiates our numbers
remain strong. Um and yet if you look at
the number of teaching elders that are
um registered in our denomination, that
number is basically flat. It's been that
way for a number of years.
>> And and that's despite the PCA growing
and uh the proliferation of campus
ministries uh within RUF, for example.
we we we don't track how many more added
burden uh burdens we have in the PCA uh
uh for ministers for teaching elders but
that's also part of the RUF campus
ministry. I was with Andrew Ryan, our
direct coordinator for RUF, and they
cannot find um enough campus ministers
to fill slots um as as we think about
growth. And everywhere I go, as Lig
said, we're seeing churches not find
qualified candidates, not find enough
candidates to fill the opportunities
across the PCA. This is just sort of
standard conversation across the PCA.
now.
>> Um, and and I and I think that it brings
up an important point. I know we're
going to get to this later, but it's not
just about a shortage of candidates. Uh,
as we think about the feeder, the
pipeline of of young men uh being raised
up uh to go and serve these pulpits.
We're also seeing I I like to refer to
it as the exit ramp, the exit ramp of
pastors out of PCA pulpit has
accelerated.
um our conversation with Geneva benefits
that tracks this particular of our
existing pastors um and and my friend uh
Ed Ed Dunnington who leads that work and
Paul Joiner who's with him but uh what
they've told us is that we've seen a 54%
increase um an acceleration of pastors
out of pulpits in the PCA since 2017.
Um, and that that's a a collection of
basically four reasons why we're seeing
pastors leave pulpits. One is moral
failure. Of course, we're aware of that
one, but we're also seeing pastors leave
because of burnout and um just
overwhelmed with the the stress of
ministry leadership and then pastors
departing the PCA, transferring out, and
then early retirements.
Um, and so for all four of those
reasons, we're we're seeing uh new
pulpits open up at an accelerated rate.
And so that's distressing this
conversation as well. Um, and so both of
these convers the raising up of new
candidates, the acceleration of of
candidates out of pulpits is creating
this demand um and uh creating the
problem. Uh so so this is definitely a
problem for for us in the PCA and and
other denominations as you mentioned uh
Derek uh and and as as Lian said I see
this in those reformed adjacent
denominations e the EPC eco um yeah
every everywhere.
>> Yeah. So I'd like to dive deeper into
what you're touching on there Tom which
is kind of some of the reasons for this.
So we've talked a little bit about
demographics.
You're talking about I heard you mention
burnout. Um some of that was early
retirement. What might be other factors
that are leading to leading to this
challenge not just now but maybe in the
coming future? Um I mean is are are we
facing issues with or different things
going on with recruitment of of young
men? Is there a training issue? Is there
a process issue, a financial issue? What
what is uh leading to some of the
shortages in the men coming up? Yeah,
that's a great question. And when I when
we talk about this uh Covenant just
received and and y'all are aware of this
a $10 million grant by the Lily
Endowment and the focus of this grant is
uh the collective work of the PCA to
raise up the next generation. I think uh
it's more important than it ever has
ever been in the life of the PTA for us
to think about our collective
responsibility to raise up the next
generation. Um we tended to be more
passive in our recruitment strategies in
previous years. We just saw this ground
swell of young men who were interested
in going to serve as pastors pastors for
a number of different reasons. But God
just in his providence and his kindness,
his mercy, we just saw this ground swell
of of young men go to seek uh to be
pastors. That was the movement of which
I was a part of. All of our seminaries
were filled in the 1990s. Every seminary
was, you know, busting at its uh its
enrollment. Um since then we've seen a
shift and um I think part of the reason
is that young people are less interested
in pursuing a life in ministry. Yeah.
>> Um but part of the reason for that is
we've seen in Gen Z, the rising
generation. Um we see this um uh we've
seen more of them walking away from the
church and we we do hear anecdotally
about stories of young men coming back
into the church and th those statistics
are going to settle out over the next
few years. But um but there has been
fewer candidates to think about
ministry, more skepticism about the
institutional church. All of those
reasons perhaps contributing to this
problem. Um we also just don't have our
churches thinking intentionally about uh
raising up the next generation. Um they
don't see themselves as agents of
responsibility in this conversation. and
they sort of see it as the job of the
seminaries and maybe other ministries.
And so one of the prime uh focus areas
of this grant is creating
a pathway uh we're calling it the
pathways to vocational ministry
initiative to raise up and identify
young men who want to go on to serve um
uh in in the church. And so we're
working with uh Mission North America,
specifically Murray Lee um as well as
Chris Vogle are devising this uh program
that can be implemented in churches and
campus ministries um and colleges across
the PCA to help us identify these young
men for uh for future ministry. And I'll
stop, but uh but that's just some of the
things I've been thinking about in this
area.
>> Lincoln, do you have anything to add to
that? Yeah, let me let me agree and just
elaborate a little bit. Uh Derek, I do
think that uh if if you look at the last
15 years of church life in the
evangelical world especially and in our
reformed part of the evangelical world,
>> we've gone through first the abuse
crisis,
then enormous racial tensions and and
wrestling through what that means for
evangelicalism,
and then COVID hits us. So for 15 years,
young men and and look, young women too
that are thinking about serving in RUF
and other church related are watching
church leaders get beat into pulps
>> and they're going, hm, I I'm not sure I
want to sign up for that. So you've
you've had a dynamic where church
leaders were scrutinized and in a
polarized setting. You could have the
same guy and and part of his
congregation thinks he's gone too far in
responding to COVID and the other part
of his congregation thinks he hasn't
gone far enough and he's the bad guy.
Even even if he is collectively trying
to figure this out with the elders of
the church, he's the bad guy.
>> So you've had that sort of a dynamic.
But on top of this, we still find that
the number one obstacle for people
starting and then timely completing
their uh seminary work in preparation
for ministry is financial. And so I I
agree with the things that Tom is
talking about doing. We need to do those
things. And by the way, we're trying to
do it through what we're calling the
Calo project just from the from the
Greek uh form I call uh and you can go
to the RTS website and look at what
we're trying to do. It's going to be
probably very similar to what Tom at
Covenant Seminary are doing. And we we
do want to equip our pastors and
churches to be more proactive. I totally
agree with Tom on that. We we that that
is something I I'll just give you a
statistic. Um we try to do entrance and
exit exams uh not of theological and
biblical issues but of what what why did
you come to seminary? What made you what
was the process? Did an RUF campus
minister recommend you to do this? Did a
did your local church pastor how tell us
about the process of how you got here?
And then when students leave, we try and
find out about what their experience
was. We want to get better at what we
do. Uh because I I know Tom agrees on
this. The better job we do in seminary,
the easier it is for us to recruit the
next generation because our graduates go
out and say, "Hey, I had a really good
experience at Covenant Seminary. I had a
really good experience at RTS. You ought
to consider it." So, we want to do the
best job we can. But 3 to one,
>> our incoming students tell tell us that
they have self- selected this vocational
path into ministry. In other words, it's
not been a minister that said, you know
what, I think you're called a pastoral
ministry. It's not even been a campus
minister that has said, you know what, I
think you're called a pastoral ministry.
It's 3:1 self- selected. I'd love to
know what Tom's numbers are on that, but
I bet you that they're similar. And what
that says to me is of of course the Holy
Spirit usually starts working in our
hearts through other things in the means
of grace whether it's the preaching of
God's word or fellowship in the context
of a campus ministry. Uh and so that
that's natural that there would be a
personal internal sense of hey I want to
do this but I'd like to see the church
[snorts]
the denomination more proactively
involved in that process. Derek, and and
I want to equip pastors to be a little
bit more aggressive, not trying to take
the place of the Holy Spirit. We can't
call people to the ministry, but but
encouraging young people who might not
to consider a vocational pathway into
gospel ministry. And I think I'm sure
that's what Tom wants to do. We want to
do the same thing, too. And I I just I
see enough of of the passive approach
that Tom described earlier still out
there and that will not work now. It
will not work. We have got to be more
involved. We've got to be more
intentional. Yeah. I I think I think the
last point that Lian was was um
emphasizing there is really critical and
and that and just the the idea of the
church as a body of Christ and ecosystem
um and an organism of collective work
and we tend to think about uh ministry
training recruitment it's sort of siloed
I think in most people's minds and we're
moving into a season in the life of the
church where We just can't think of
ourselves as um a a sort of a solitary
task performing a function for the
church that's isolated from the broader
body of Christ. We are integrated in
that work. and whether we're a
denominational seminary or a seminary
like RTS that essentially serves the PCA
and and and like-minded denominations
but very closely tethered to the life of
the church. We have to see ourselves as
in partnership with the church which is
to say that churches have to see um the
raising up of future ministers and
ministry leaders. We think about not
just men but also women, those who are
going to serve in vocational ways the
life of the church. We have to help them
see that this is one of their
responsibilities. This is one of their
jobs. And and and as we think about
churches, um uh you know, attendance is
great, right? Attendance is great. Um
new programs of ministry, uh those are
great. But essential to this task is the
disciplehip of our young people. If they
aren't being discipled in a significant
way such that they're integrating their
Christian view of the world into their
life, we know that their faith will not
um stick. And and that's essential to
this whole idea of raising up uh a
generation of ministry leaders is that
these people are being discipled and
catechized in our tradition in the faith
such that they want to go multiply and
see it um lived out in a vocational way.
And that fundamentally is the work of
the church. Um and we have to we have to
be intentional about that work. We have
to stir the imagination of our young
people just like we would stir their
imagination for a career in medicine or
law or engineering um or education. We
need to be doing that with uh our young
people to think about life in the
church. Again, not to take the place of
the Holy Spirit, but also not to act as
though we're not intentional agents. I
mean, God has called us to be those who
exercise the means um uh to participate
in the in the work of God. And we do
that as we inspire young people to think
about a future life in ministry. So now
when I'm with churches and they're
asking me about the work of Covenant
Seminary and how they can participate,
um I I say, "Well, don't wait until your
children are in college to talk to them
about a possible future in in ministry."
is we need to be having those
conversations in middle school and early
high school. And I think that's a that's
an attitudinal shift for uh for most of
our churches. And then secondly, for
them to see themselves as vital partners
with seminaries, in fact, upstream of
this conversation and in some ways more
important um to this conversation than
maybe they thought they ever were.
>> Amen.
>> That's great. Um, so let me let me can I
if I could tell a little personal
narrative here of how this intersects
with this and my own calling into
ministry. When I was in college, I was
hearing John Piper's sea shell sermon
and that was hugely inspirational for me
and a lot of people I knew. And it just,
you know, it was this, you know, do you
have a passion to serve the Lord with
your life? And at that time, you know,
if you wanted to serve the Lord,
generally speaking, that meant you went
into ministry, right? And I think a lot
of people recognized over time that we
needed a a broader and more balanced
view of vocation that you can serve God
in all sorts of vocations. And in some
ways that I feel like has led the
pendulum swing the other direction. So
now it's uh serve God in anything you do
which is true but it's de it's uh in
some ways taken away from u people's
options at least in their thinking and
imagination the idea of going into
ministry. And it seems like we need to
kind of we need to balance out where we
we can both say yes you can serve God in
any vocation in any calling and also
being a pastor is a great calling and we
need pastors. We need people to go into
ministry.
>> Yeah.
>> I Eric I agree and let me just say that
that is a conversation that I had over
the course of the last two years of Tim
Keller's life. Tim and I taught
introduction to pastoral and theological
studies at RTS New York City for seven
years together. And one of the things
that he said and and of course he was a
very instrumental in cultivating the
faith and work movement in our neck of
the woods. And he said, you know, I
think there's probably been a little of
an overcorrection there and and we need
to challenge some guys. Yeah, you can be
a godly hedge fund manager and make
millions, but you could also consider
going into gospel ministry and serving
in the church. And I I do think there's
a both and there. Yeah. But we need to
make sure that we're also looking for
people that are going to be committing
themselves vocationally especially
>> to uh the ministry of uh the means in
the churches.
>> Yep.
>> Let's let's keep pressing in this
direction. Are there maybe a few
particular ways that each of you would
want to encourage churches and
presbyaries to be intentional about
raising up future leaders? You've
already mentioned a few of those. Just
um you know pointing it out to some
guys. Have you considered this? I mean
that's a that's a very obvious thing
that we need to be doing more. But are
there maybe more structural things we
can be doing as churches and
presbyteries to help guys get into
ministry? I'm thinking here maybe
financial arrangements with helping with
seminary or certain types of internships
or partnerships between churches. I
think one of the challenges in going
into ministry or raising up guys is if
you're a small church and you think,
"Oh, this guy might be called," but we
as an individual church don't have the
resources to send him to seminary.
>> How do we how do we get them there? You
know, so do you guys have any thoughts
on how we could be doing that as
churches and presbyaries?
>> Lean, you go. Why don't you go first?
[laughter]
>> Uh I know Tom and I both have a lot of
things we want to say about this. One is
to pastors, I I I would say and
especially in churches with more
resources, I would say have interns, pay
them and pay their tuition to go to
seminary. And if you do, it's a winwin
win.
Um, it's a win for you. You will never
pay less for good talent
>> in your church than you will for an
intern. It's a win for me and for Tom
because it means we don't have to go out
and raise the support to pay for their
tuition because if they did if you
didn't pay for tuition, Tom and I are
going to be paying for that tuition. I
assure you it's nobody nobody's going to
come sweeping in and do it. Tom and I
are going to be out there trying to
figure out how to pay for their because
we want them to be serving in the church
and we don't want money to be the thing
that keeps them from it. So, you're
super duper helping the student, but
you're helping us. Um, number three,
it's a blessing for that local church.
Uh, that that local church, you know,
there are young, super godly, talented
people that are going to be a blessing
to your congregation and it's a blessing
to the future church because you're
helping equip somebody who hopefully is
going to serve 30, 40, maybe even 50
years in gospel ministry. So, that's one
thing that I say to folks. I think
another thing, and I bet Tom and I are
going to be going around the country
saying this for the next however long
the Lord gives us, is to raise awareness
of the issue that we're talking about
today. You would be surprised how many
people, especially in the pews and
especially on sessions, are completely
oblivious to the dynamics that we're
talking about today. Pastors are more
aware of them, I think, than they were 5
years ago. and and we need to continue
to doing a good job of of raising
pastoral awareness, but congregations
are not, you know, they're they're
involved in their lives. There are
things that are going on. They're not
thinking about the pipeline. Now,
everywhere I go, Tom's right, pastors
are talking about pipeline, but there
are a lot of people in the congregation
that are not. So, we need to continue to
raise awareness uh about this. I think
we also and Tom's already said it, we
need to be very proactive in our
identification of people who are
potentially uh have the character, the
calling and the gifting to serve. And we
just need to uh cultivate proactivity
there and and and supply um resources to
help pastors and elders and churches
identify and equip that that my my
church did this for me. Uh, you know, if
if Paul Settle and Gordon Reed when I
was a pre-teen and a teen had not done
the ministry that they did, had Wallace
Kinsley not done the ministry that he
did in my life, I wouldn't have been at
Covenant Seminary, I wouldn't have gone
to Edinburgh, I wouldn't have come back
uh to be a PCA minister. People invested
just like Tom was saying at a very young
age in me. I I was not yet 14 when under
my youth pastor, I had a definite
personal sense that this is what I need
to prepare for. And I actually went to
the elders at the at barely the age of
14 and said, "Would you give me
opportunities to serve in the church and
see if I have the the the the the gifts
and the abilities that are necessary for
me to serve this way?" And I'm
profoundly thankful that people started
and I think all of us need to think
exactly what Tom said, start when they
are teenagers.
>> Uh, and wonderful organizations like RM
and things like that are going to
provide us pathways into that world. But
we need to be talking to youth directors
about being aware of this. We need to be
talking to elders that are in charge of
youth committees thinking about this as
well as pastors and sessions. And then I
would I would just say don't think that
um seminaries can just do what we do
effortlessly. Uh Tom Tom can can join me
in testifying in saying it's a miracle
that we're able to do what we're able to
do. Your prayer and your support for our
seminaries is very important. At the
last general assembly during the M&A
report, one of the things that kind of
caught my attention, and I'm I'm almost
certain this number must come from
Murray, is that there was something like
800 people in the pipeline for ministry
in the PCA. Now, I don't know where that
starts, Derek, and where, you know,
where they are along the way, but if
that number is anywhere close, and if I
know Murray, it's close. It said to me
that the traditional seminaries and
especially Covenant, Westminster, RTS,
Westminster, California,
we're actually preparing most of those
people. And so in a day and age where
people talk about alternative pathways
to ministry and and and look, I'm I'm
not against alternative pathways.
Your traditional seminaries are still
going to be the main suppliers. And if
you don't support them, it is going to
hamper their ability to supply the
ministry of the church. There's going to
be no more efficient way to supply that
ministry than to pray for and support
our seminary. So, uh just take take that
as uh as a word of support for Covenant
Seminary as well. Uh Tom,
well, let me jump in. Lian, I I 100%
agree with everything that he's saying
and support that. uh I go back to some
of the ear the earlier uh portions of of
of this part of the conversation but
just the financial burden of uh students
have as they contemplate going on for
theological study. It's a significant um
concern that uh students have and they
they're already perhaps experiencing
debt from their undergraduate period and
they don't want to um bring on more debt
as they anticipate a future in ministry
that is not going to be able to address
that debt through their compensation.
And so um church donations, church
partnerships, scholarships,
um uh sessions who are willing to pay
tuition for uh for an ordinance or a
seminary student, those things are
critical uh to students um entertaining
a call to ministry. And um again, it's
it's just another facet of how churches
need to think about mission. Um mi
mission is is um it's broad as we think
about the calling of the church. Um but
part of our mission is to not just guard
the deposit but to ensure that those who
are going to guard that deposit are
being raised up.
>> Yeah.
>> And and this is the whole task of
recruiting and training and identify
those whom God is calling. And and our
participation as the church is to supply
those needs to resource that young
person. as I was headed off to seminary,
my congregation in Birmingham, I was so
grateful for Alan Carter who was a
graduate of RTS. Um, but uh, for his
leadership and disciplehip personally of
me as and and then that congregation to
participate and partner with me as I
headed off to seminary. And we need all
of our churches across the PCA doing
that work. And the reality is it's even
more important now than it was 30 years
ago. That's what people don't
understand. is the need is greater now.
Um, as students think about uh the the
price tag essentially of theological
education and and and as Lian said, our
our institutions are hard at work not
just recruiting scholarship docu uh
dollars, but um all of uh the distance a
tuition dollar is going to go is not
nearly what it was 30 years ago. And so
donations and scholarships are essential
to seminaries fulfilling their function.
The other thing I would just say as we
think about the disciplehip of our young
people, another place where we're
continuing to see uh people young people
called into ministry is is not really
from the church, but it's in the context
of uh campus ministries where young
people are being reached for Christ. And
so they haven't grown up in the church.
Um and uh in short order they're
experiencing a conversion and then a
call to ministry and they haven't built
the kind of thick background in the life
of the church. They haven't been
catechized in our confessional standards
and and they're coming into seminary and
they're wanting the seminary to to do
all of that work as it were that
disciplehip. Um and and this is another
uh uh aspect of how the church can get
involved is realizing that our
commitment to to these other ministries
like RUF and CO is so critical because
these are the the fishing pools as it
were for reaching the next generation.
And if you weren't engaged in those
places, we're not raising up the next
generation. I didn't myself grow up in
the PCA. I grew up in the mainline
Presbyterian church and I experienced a
call to ministry through RUF at Auburn
University and this is where my faith
took root and came alive and I
experienced that call to ministry. And
we want to see that story reproduced.
And we see that story reproduced not
only in campus ministry settings but
also in church planting settings, places
where we're seeing the vitality of the
gospel uh at its most vibrant. Um those
are the places where we're going to see
people uh being one to Christ, discipled
um unto maturity and then called to
ministry. And we want our churches to
have that kind of mindset as they think
about the next generation because in
those places where the Holy Spirit is
working, that's where you're going to
see people called to ministry. And so
those are vital places um for us to be
thinking about this task. And this is
part of the reason why in the Lily Grant
I was referring to a few moments ago,
we're partnering with Covenant College.
Um we're partnering with Geneva College.
We're partnering with Geneva Benefits
and Mission North America um so that
we're activating all of these fishing
pools uh for the purpose of raising up
the next generation.
So, one of the um longstanding
challenges Presbyterians have faced when
it comes to raising up new ministers is
that non-denoms and Baptist churches,
you know, all the way back in the
frontier days,
>> they could get a guy, you know,
converted and ordain him a week later
and send him out. Whereas the
Presbyterians were sending their guys
back east to get trained. And we still
face a some a similar barrier in that
regard. We've got pretty high standards,
right, with with an undergraduate
degree, seminary degree, internship, and
all that. You know, do you guys have any
thoughts on how we balance maintaining
high standards, you know, character that
that kind of experience in the church
you were talking about, Tom, competency,
doctrinal knowledge, and fidelity. How
do we maintain those high standards, but
also be aware of ways we may be
unintentionally creating unnecessary
barriers for men who might be called to
the ministry? Is that something you guys
could speak to at all?
>> Yeah, I'll I'll tackle that one because
it goes back to something that Le had
mentioned. I think that 800 number comes
from our stated clerk's report and uh
the candidates for ministry. There's I
was looking back at that there were 802
candidates for ministry in 2025 and and
uh I I think we've seen that number uh
hover around that 750 to 800 for the
last several years which is great but
we're not seeing new teaching elders in
similar proportions and and so I think
that one of the questions we're having
is seeing that translation so candidates
going on and being trained and
being ordained. That's the critical uh
gap if if there is a gap and um and then
placed and and as we think about um are
our standards too high,
you know, it's always a a a challenge,
right? It's always a question. Are we
requiring too much? Um I think the
scriptures lead us to think about the
character formation of our young people.
um those who would go on to serve for
good reason because we see the
pressures, we see the temptations, we
see the ways in which ministers will be
tested. And for us to give priority to
the formation of those who will go on to
serve, I think is wise. And I appreciate
the priority that the PCA gives to this
question and the high standards for
character that we want to uphold,
although we don't do it perfectly. And
then as I think about their theological
preparation, again, they're handling the
mysteries, right? We're we're doing
significant and great work. And we want
our pastors and ministry leaders to be
excellently trained. I'm grateful that
we in the PCA still uphold a high
standard um for the Mdive. in an age in
which we've seen the MDB degree decline
more broadly. I think the high mark for
the MD across the US was uh 2006 roughly
35,000 students were involved in uh MD
programs. Now it's you know basically
10,000
um fewer students in MD programs across
ATS schools. But the priority of the
MDEV and also a robust degree program in
the MD is still a priority for all of
the most of the seminaries serving the
PCA. Frankly, I'm grateful for that. Um
I want us to preserve that even though
it does create challenges for us as we
think about um reaching new areas, uh
new demographics,
um uh new territories within our
country. I I saw this this was one of
our big challenges that we faced in
South Texas uh which when I went to San
Antonio was was was largely an unreached
city for the PCA and a very different
type of city for the PCA. And so
answering these questions is really
important. But I don't think our
standards are insurmountable. I think
they call forth uh strategic leadership
um and longer term planning and and
really uh the kind of um mentorship
that is going to uh serve the PCA. We
need to be invested in those whom God is
raising up and meeting those obstacles,
those barriers. Uh not really changing
our standards. That that would be my
counsel. I don't know, Lig, if um if you
agree with that. Yeah, I'd just say I'd
add two more things. We're coming up,
we're we're in the 214th year since
Princeton Seminary was started. And one
of the reasons Princeton was started was
because the the mentor model of
preparing Presbyterian pastors was not
efficient enough to get enough
Presbyterian pastors out on the fields.
And so this the seminaries were actually
helped not to be uh they were created
not to clog the pipeline, but to make
the pipeline flow better. And I I think
that still is the case today. I don't
think seminaries are the we're not the
clog in the pipeline. Now costs are a
reality, but I Tom will tell you and
I'll tell you
>> very few of my students pay what it in
fact none of my students pay what it
costs to go to seminary. I cost me twice
as much to educate somebody than if they
were to pay full tuition. And there
isn't anybody that pays full tuition at
RTS. So seminaries are bending over
backwards to help on the financial
front. And then the accredititors have
actually given us more flexibility than
ever before in the area of qualified
students that lack certain credentials
um at the undergraduate level like an
accredited bachelor's degree. the the
accredititors actually have been super
helpful because they recognize the
problem as well in giving us flexibility
about what we can do in terms of getting
a person through graduate theological
education. So I I would just say that
when people consider alternative
pathways not through the seminary, you
you have to bear in mind two things.
Number one, usually if those pathways
are high standard, they take longer than
seminaries, not shorter. So for
instance, PE the the the average number
of years for students getting accredited
online master's degrees from theological
institutions in North America is about
10 years. Well, I I think Tom and I want
to get people through faster than that.
I I want to get people through faster
and out on the field. But the other
thing that happens is in order not to
get people through in 10 years, people
lower the standards. And the fact of the
matter is in I I want to come back to
something Tom said about disciplehip.
We've got a bigger challenge with that
now than we did 30 years ago. When when
I I grew up in a world where you went to
church twice on Sunday, Wednesday night,
I I had three essential preaching
opportunities every week. Tom's right.
So many people come to faith in Christ,
praise God, through a campus outreach or
an RUF or an FCA or u a crew large group
on a college campus and they've never
had the that sort of of disciplehip in
their life and they have to get up to
speed really fast. If we lower the
standards of what our seminaries are
providing, we're in trouble because our
our people are being discipled by the
internet today. And you can say all
manner of stupid things on the internet
that anybody who had gone through a
graduate theological program of
education would would know was blowing
smoke. And you can't tell the difference
if you haven't actually been equipped.
And we've got to be equipped to help
people in a world where they're
self-educating through really inferior
sources uh that are out there. And
that's that's, you know, people I I was
just reading today about people going
into Eastern Orthodoxy because they saw
some guy on YouTube or people, you know,
it just crazy things that people are
doing. We've got to equip a ministry
that can carefully, intelligently,
lovingly speak into that world in their
in their evangelism, in their
disciplehip, in their local church
ministry, and their campus ministry. And
there's just no way that you can there's
no shortcut to that. It it just takes
time. I I I stayed at Covenant for four
years and I'm I'm so thankful that I got
to bake an extra year. I did an Mdive. I
was single, so my married friends had a
lot harder challenge than I did. But as
a single man, I took everything that I
could in my MD, got it done in three
years, stayed on and did an MA. But then
even when I went to Edinburgh, I went
next door to the Free Church College,
which is now Edinburgh Theological
Seminary. And I sat in on the theology
and church history lectures again just
for my soul because I was in a
dominantly liberal place. And I felt
like, okay, I just need something
feeding me good stuff. And baking for
six or seven years in that, even with a
wonderful disciplehip background I had
before, was really helpful uh for me.
And so I don't want to see students
shortchanged on that. I I think in fact
I I my approach now with our students is
to say
even if you stay four or five years in
an MD program while you're working at a
church here, I I I cannot teach you all
the things you need to know for a
lifetime of ministry, but I can teach
you to self-feed. Mhm.
>> And you've got to be committed to being
a lifelong learner. And this has got to
be the start. We're trying to lay a
foundation where you read scripture well
and you read theology with discernment
and where you think about how is this
supposed to work out in my life and how
is this supposed to work out in the life
of the church. But we're only going to
be able to lay the foundation. you're
going to have to continue on for the
rest of your life uh learning because we
we just have a lot of catching up to do
in our culture. And uh PCA pastors I
think feel that um and and we certainly
feel it at the seminaries. I I um
Covenant Seminary was one of the first
places that I took my leadership team
when I became the chancellor at RTS. And
I asked, we went to Dallas, we went to
Westminster, we went to Covenant, we we
tried to go to our various sister
institutions who are trying to do the
same things that we're doing. And one of
the questions I would ask the professors
is, "What are you seeing from your
students that are that are coming to
seminary?" And everybody said, "Our
students know less Bible than they knew
30 years ago." And so the seminaries end
up being the remediating
organization for that. We have to help
catch that up. And we want our people
grow. I I think we we not only are
thinking about people serving the PCA
well, but not to pat ourselves on the
back, but it is true that the PCA
supplies a lot of theological ballast
for the evangelical world. You know, I I
I I go out there and it makes me happy
when when I hear other people quoting
our PCA guys. Well, you know, so and so
says that, Bob Yarborough says this, Dan
Doriani uh says this, Scott Swain says
this. That makes me happy when I hear
them say things like that. But you you
have to invest in people to be able to
provide those people for the larger
evangelical world. And I think that's
one thing that we in the PCA need to be
thinking. How are we with our unique
Yes, we've got some quirks, but with our
unique gifts, how do we serve the larger
church body in the world? And one way we
do that is through a really
well-prepared ministry.
>> Yeah. Amen. Derek, I want to come back
to something Lick said. We're talking
about alternate pathways. And I I think
the most significant alternate pathway
is not necessarily a recast of
traditional theological education. It's
more about the delivery mechanism
>> and it's it's the online modality.
>> And what we've seen over the last say 15
20 years is just this uh um shift from
residential theological education to the
online space. And um there there are a
number of uh advantages of that, but
there are also some some real
liabilities and and one of them um uh
Lian mentioned and these are not
necessarily
um top of mind for most future students
when they when they start the online
program, they don't think it's going to
take them longer um to work. They think
this is more efficient.
>> Yeah. The reality is it might be
significantly less efficient. The other
thing that I would just highlight, and
this is not to take a shot at online
theological education. We're deeply
invested in that at Covenant Seminary.
We love our online and hybrid program,
especially our hybrid program for the
MD. But but what we know is that
students are less likely to persist in
their degree program unless they become
very serious about it, especially early.
Um we've seen the likelihood of students
persisting um ba basically our students
won't persist in their degree program
unless they get to 23 credits
which is roughly 25% of their degree.
And if students are languishing, so if
they take one course and then skip a
semester, take another course and then
skip a semester, they do that for a
couple of years, the likelihood of them
persisting is is greatly diminished. And
and so one of the things Lig said and
and I agree with him is this is going to
take you longer if you do it in the
online space. Um it's not just going to
take you longer, you may actually not
finish your goal.
>> Yeah. because the reality of all of the
other aspects of life are going to be
bearing down on you. And this is where I
would ask for a special dispensation
from our pastors
>> because um one of the ways they feel
distressed
about finding new candidates is they is
when they find a great candidate who's
serving as say a youth director or a
ministry team leader and then that
person is experiencing a call to
ministry and they want to go to
seminary. that pastor is now uh vexed
because they have to decide to let that
pastor go um and go do residential
theological education and then that
immediately surfaces replacement and
they're asking that question who can do
this job. Online theological education
comes into the rescue, right? um which
is great but but it introduces another
problem that that person may not be
thinking about and that is the quality
of their uh education. How much time are
they actually going to be able to give
to sit and as Lian was saying bake to
bake in the beauty of the resource that
is available in an institution like a
covenant or like an RTS to sit with
those professors and so what we've
really begun to see at Covenant and I
just want to encourage uh our listeners
to think about this is to see online
theological education as a wonderful
opportunity but perhaps best served as
an on-ramp to finally getting to do
residential theological education where
you can do that baking and sitting and
um have the time where uh you're
experiencing uh educators, professors,
experts in their field who basically
wake up every morning and have given
their lives to asking the question, how
can I train the next generation of
pastors and ministry leaders? um as
opposed to what's the next ministry
program responsibility I have and then
how am I getting my Greek done uh at
9:00 on a Friday night. That's exactly
>> those are real questions that people
face
>> and we want our future pastors and
ministry leaders to have the time
>> to do theological education well and and
I know there are so many different
burdens bearing down on our on our on
our um our our students. But these are
important things for them to consider as
as they they contemplate alternate
pathways um uh because um there there
there are many different challenges
associated with with uh the choices that
they make.
>> Yeah, let me Derek let me amen what Tom
said and add three quick things. Number
one, Tom is not just being negative
about online. A lot of people don't know
Covenant Seminary, Reformed Theological
Seminary, and Bethl Seminary were the
first three seminaries approved to do
distance learning by the Association of
Theological Schools. So, we have been in
this game for a long time. And Covenant
and RTS, we do the very best job we can
with online resources for the church.
So, we're not just saying this to poo
poo online education. But the second
thing to add, exactly what Tom said, is
this. The self-discipline that it takes
you to get without classmates around
you, with without being in the presence
of your professors, to get through a
full theological program of of MD,
preparation for ministry. I I wouldn't
have had the self-discipline to do that.
I'm very thankful for the structure of a
residential MD. And and even as Tom and
I, we've we have hybrid programs as well
that are designed to help people get
into the regularity
of their theological preparation, which
is really really hard unless you are Mr.
Super duper self-discipline if you're
doing online on your own. And the third
thing, uh Tom is right about retention.
We do see a lot of people start and not
finish. And we don't want to we don't
want to see that uh happen. But the
other thing I would say is this.
While a person is preparing for
ministry, I want their main thoughts to
be on that preparation for ministry,
not that preparation for ministry to be
peripheral to everything else. And I
don't mean that I don't want them
involved in ministry. Let me give my
testimony. I at Covenant Seminary for
four years, I got to be the youth
director at the Covenant Presbyterian
Church.
And I loved the combination of working
at the church and studying at the
seminary. And I it got to be it got to
be an outlet of what I was learning in
the seminary. You'll laugh at me, Derek,
but my my high school students wanted to
study Calvin's Institutes because they
heard me talking about David Calhoun's
Calvin's Institutes course. And so guess
what we did? We went through Calvin's
Institutes with my high school students
and they loved it. their parents thought
I was crazy, but the students loved it.
Um, you know, I I was giving to them
what I was learning in seminary. And so,
it was a wonderful environment, but all
the time while I was enjoying ministry,
my focus was preparing for a lifetime of
ministry. And it's really hard to do a
good job of that if that is peripheral
to to what you're really focused on. And
so it's super hard for somebody that's
only doing it online for that to be the
thing that's occupying your heart and
your mind when it's a ministry is fun.
And it's a whole lot more fun to be
discipling somebody over lunch at the
corner drugstore than it is to be
studying for a Greek exam. But but but
there are some things that are worth
investing ourselves in that are going to
pay dividends for the rest of our life
that if they're not pretty central to
what we're doing will be lost. And so
for those reasons, I want to agree 100%
with what time just said.
>> Yeah. If I could offer just some of what
we're doing at at my church that really
speaks to the the challenges y'all are
both raising about online or hybrid. Um,
we're basically we're trying to have
regular meetings with the people that
are in seminary that are at our church
and to try to provide some sort of that
of that classroom sharpening uh context
just in our local church and checking in
with with people. How is how are your
studies going? What are you reading?
Because it is it is an issue of
motivation. It's also not having that
residential program. you're not getting
as much of that theological sharpening
and you know out of class debate or
dialogue that goes on. And so uh we're
trying to create an ecosystem here. We
have about four seminary students at our
church and we're a pretty we're not a
huge church. And uh that's that's
something I've really enjoyed. But I do
think it has it's playing a factor in
them continuing in their studies. I
think if they didn't have that, it'd be
too easy for that to fall by the
wayside. So
>> yeah.
>> All right. To wrap this up because I
want to honor y'all's time. Do you all
have any thoughts on uh just placement
uh of ministers? Uh and if not that, you
could speak to just what is encouraging
to you about the current landscape.
We'll we'll kind of end with those.
>> Good.
>> Okay, Tom.
>> Uh yeah. Well, I think I think um
placement especially in an environment
like the the PCA, other our our sister
denominations like the EPC
um is always going to be enhanced by the
development of ministry networks. Um and
by being embedded in ministry networks,
uh placement in the in the PCA and in
just most ministry settings is not
transactional. Um it is uh it is
relational. And so again we have to see
ourselves in partnership with the
church. And so having our young people
um participating in presbyteries like
participating in the candidate and
lentious pro lentia uh process um uh de
developing relationships in the city
where they're attending seminary like
Lian talked about working in a in a
local church. I I was an intern in a
local actually at Covenant Church as
well.
>> Wow. when I was at seminary. And and so
those relationships are critical and
they don't just serve a young person for
those four years or those three years or
5 years that they're at seminary. Those
relationships are essential to a
lifetime of ministry.
>> Yeah.
>> The the people and the relationships
that I formed in the 1990s at Covenant
Theological Seminary are still among the
most important relationships in my life.
um where I regularly interact and pray
with and come alongside those
relationships. They've continued to feed
me um and serve the gospel in my heart
across um now three decades of of
ministry. And and so that's the thing I
just want to emphasize is is um God is
working through the relationships of his
of his people.
And and and and so then the other thing
that you were bringing up and I know we
want to wrap this up and just in terms
of what's encouraging me. I I know there
are many challenges and we look at the
statistics and um sometimes they can be
discouraging but statistics uh they
don't tell us about the future, they
tell us about the past and and and what
encourages me is the conversations I'm
having with this current generation of
student. Um th though there are many
obstacles as Lig said they are
intentionally coming to seminary wanting
to serve in the church.
>> Yeah.
>> Uh with their eyes wide open.
>> They're here even though they know the
challenges that are in front of them.
>> And that should be one of the most
encouraging things for our church. Um
yeah, this generation of young people um
uh they they inspire me as um they want
to dig into the word of God and they
want to ask the hard questions and
wrestle with the implications of their
faith. um even as they see their peers
um the the the people that they grew up
with in their communities um uh walking
away, they feel a burden um that is so
encouraging to me. Um, and so there
there are, yes, challenges that we're
facing in the church, but I would just
want to encourage your listeners, um,
and those of us in the PCA to to one,
pray for and be excited about this
future generation because their eyes are
wide open and they're here and they're
ready to go serve. Um, and that's just
one of the the bright spots for me as I
serve here at Covenant Seminary.
>> Yeah. Yeah. I agree with everything Tom
said. I'll add a couple of things. Uh
with regard to placement, right now at
RTS over the last x number of years,
we've had either 100% or almost 100%
placement in every program. Uh you know,
within 3 to 6 months of graduation. I
mean, it's just amazing. And that's
partly because we're Covenant RTS. We
serve healthy church bodies. Praise God.
I I wake up every day and I'm thankful
for the PCA and the ARP and the OPC and
the EPC and the the co conservative
non-denominational
uh church networks that we serve.
They're healthy, they're alive, and they
need pastors. And so placement is not
near the challenge for us than it is for
seminaries that are serving dying
constituencies. And so, uh, you know,
that said, placement is, as Tom said,
relational. And we've always had, I bet
Tom has the same thing. Somebody calls
me up and says, "I need a pastor. I've
got a guy on faculty." That's the first
call I make because he's just great at
seeing fit. This guy would fit here. But
we've realized we need to be we need to
be better at that. And so we're in the
middle of a we're we're in a a quiet
phase of a major capital campaign. And
one part of that capital campaign is to
raise some money for one person that all
he's going to do is coordinate placement
uh across RTS and facilitate placement
of our students because I don't want
just them to be placed. I want the fit
to be right. I want them to be in the
right place with the right church in the
right job description and such. And so
I'm I'm sure Tom is going to be doing
this and is doing this himself. So we
are trying to figure out how can we do a
better job of that, Derek. And I would
also say, as Tom indicated, I I love our
students. Uh you know, they they make me
happy. uh their convictions, uh their
commitments, uh their their willingness
to face uh greater opposition from the
culture than I did when I graduated from
seminary in the 1980s and yet go out
confident in the gospel, believing the
Bible, knowing that Jesus is the answer,
uh ready to proclaim the word, ready to
minister to hurting uh people. It just
it's it's a joy to I' I've been doing
this for 36 years and u I've I've never
enjoyed my students more than I do now.
And again, I don't take that for granted
because I know what's happening in other
places. Um you know, in the I I grew up
in the the what was called the old
southern church, the PCUS, that
eventually joined with the PCUSA. RTS
alone has more candidates for ministry
than all the PCUSA seminaries put
together. And that's not a tribute to
us. It's it's the it points to the fact
that there is they're serving a dying
denomination. Um, and so, you know, Tom
and I are blessed to be in the best
possible place in the world right now to
be doing theological education in North
America in terms of our constituency, in
terms of the people that God is bringing
to us. And we just want to do the best
job we can when we I I tell people I
just don't want to ruin them when they
come to me. I want to make sure they go
out better than when I got them because
they're wonderful young people.
>> Well, that's great, guys. I I'm so
thankful for both of you uh and for the
work y'all are doing um that's serving
not just our denomination but the church
as a whole. Uh I think for me uh one of
the takeaways is we need to pray to the
Lord of the harvest that he'd raise up
more workers um and trust that he'll
provide what we need and then be
diligent to to kind of apply some of the
things you guys are talking about to be
strategic about how we encourage young
men and walk with them and resource them
and partner to get together to get them
in the right place. So, thank you all
both for your time and uh I'm sure we'll
see you around and and continue to hear
good things that you guys are doing. So,
thank you.
>> Thank you, Derek.
>> Thanks so much, Derek. Appreciate you.
Appreciate you, Lian.
>> And thank you, Tom.
>> All right.